Alex Shulaev

Senior Front End Developer | Engineering Manager

Armenia, Yerevan | <u>alexandrshy@gmail.com</u> <u>github.com/Alexandrshy</u> | <u>linkedin.com/in/alexandrshy</u> | <u>t.me/alexandrshy</u>

SUMMARY

Front End Developer with more than 8 years of experience. My main technical stack: TypeScript/JavaScript, HTML, CSS, React, Redux, Jest, React Testing Library, Node.js, PostCSS, ESLint, Prettier. I am engaged in creating user-friendly interfaces that effectively solve business problems. For the last two years I have expanded my skills to include technical management in the role of team leader. My goal is to use my experience to solve larger tasks and contribute to the company's success.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Optimax Dev | Software Engineering Manager

Jan. 2022 - Present

- Streamlined and documented the onboarding process for new developers, team decision-making
 procedures, and one-on-one meeting protocols, leading to significant improvements in Employee
 Satisfaction and Employee Retention Metrics, reaching 90% while effectively increasing developer retention
 without impacting the budget.
- Devised a career roadmap for developers aspiring to become team leaders, accelerating the internal promotion and external recruitment of engineering leaders by 25%.
- Designed and implemented an MVP for the design system using a React + Styled Components stack and CI/CD based on GitHub Actions. The development of the design system enhanced performance and elevated Web Vitals metrics into the "green zone." Utilized semantic-release for automatic documentation of releases, driven by commit messages, resulting in a 90% reduction in time spent on manual documentation.

Optimax Dev | Senior Engineering Lead

Dec 2019 - Jan 2022

- Served as Engineering Lead for the Analytics team, collecting and supplying user action and preference data to the Data team.
- Transitioned to organizing and leading the Product Labs team, focusing on A/B testing and personalization of user experience after successfully establishing the Analytics team.
- Implemented a modal window widget using Module Federation in webpack, optimizing site loading speed by offloading code from the main bundle.Reduce core bundle size by 8%. Stack: Svelte, TypeScript, Testing Library.
- Introduced a tool for displaying unique client recommendations, increasing conversion rates by 15% for returning users.
- Conducted global refactoring of critical experiments, reducing experiment package size by 30% and load time by 40%.
- Integrated Web Vitals metrics to monitor performance changes after introducing new features, ensuring optimal metric performance.
- Developed a template for new repositories, halving the time required for creating new packages.
- Implemented a package of helper-functions, eliminating code duplication in the main repository.

Optimax Dev | Senior Front End Developer

Aug 2018 - Dec 2019

Integrated Google Analytics, Dynamic Yield, and Impact Radius for improved user insights, personalization,
 A/B testing, and marketing programs, resulting in a 50% reduction in hypothesis testing time, a 32% increase

in CTR for new users, a 7% improvement in CR for all users, and a 10% decrease in the marketing budget. These improvements significantly increased company profits.

- Transitioned over 2,000 files from Flow to TypeScript due to declining Flow support and lack of a development roadmap, leading to enhanced IDE support and easier onboarding.
- Introduced the first iteration of automated E2E testing with Puppeteer, reducing regression testing time by 48%.

Retail Rocket | Front End Developer

Apr 2017 - Jul 2018

- Developed over 60 embeddable widgets utilizing JavaScript, HTML, CSS, and various frameworks.
- Created templates for email newsletters and marketing widgets, reducing new feature delivery time to production by approximately 25%.
- Established a code review process, leading to a decrease in the number of bugs.
- Coordinated technical meetings for the frontend department, enabling effective management of technical debt and timely updates to the codebase.

Gildiya PRO | Front End Developer

Oct 2015 - Jul 2018

- Successfully delivered 16 projects spanning diverse industries, adhering to established deadlines. Technical stack: JavaScript, Knockout, jQuery, HTML, SASS.
- Designed an interface for the internal CMS, providing a comprehensive solution for clients and enhancing the user experience for administrators.
- Mentored and trained new Front End Developer, contributing to the growth of the frontend department from one to eight members, which facilitated an increase in the number of projects executed.

SKILLS

Technical skills: JavaScript, TypeScript, HTML, CSS, React, Redux, Jest, React Testing Library, Node.js, styled-components, PostCSS, webpack, Svelte, ESLint, Prettier

Management skills: Mentoring, People Management, Team Building, Team Management, Business Process Improvement, Forming and supporting a community

LANGUAGES

English (Professional working proficiency), Russian (Native)

EDUCATION

Bachelor, Applied Information Technology, Tolyatti State University

2012 - 2016

GPA 4.8 / 5

PROJECTS

Microblog on technical management | https://t.me/softlead [in Russian]

• I write notes after reading books, attending meetups, or from personal experience. The main task is to take notes on the material I've learned. I use this project as a journal of notes that I can refer to when mentoring in the future

Mentoring | https://getmentor.dev

Jul. 2022 - Present

Provided professional consultations for front end developers and team leads.